[Music]
indeed every time you work in
mathematics you should hear tadashi's
voice in your head saying ah it might be
better to draw a picture for this so I
sh here is the picture
of the space of all n byn
matrices I told you that our pictures
will not be physical representations of
physical object that's the picture big
space and inside the space there might
be many many different elements so for
example here you may not see it because
it's very small is the identity Matrix
here is another Matrix here is another
Matrix and so on but the point is that
the
majority of this space most of this
space yeah is
filled by invertible
[Applause]
matrices yeah and the bit that is not
invertible there might be some bits is a
very thin set
so this is the
very th
subset of non-
[Applause]
inverti if you are somewhere
here then if you move slightly in the
vicinity nearby you stay invertible but
if you're somewhere here just sitting
here if you move a little you fall off
this very
scept yes how do you know about this oh
because of ah maybe I should have
explain because of that discussion we
had about the zero
determinant because a function being
zero is a very very unstable condition
you see if you have a matrix whose
determinant is zero and if you change
the entries of the Matrix a little bit
which means I sort of Kick It in various
directions slightly well
your M determinant is going to stop
being zero will become non
zero yeah of course that's what you mean
that's what you would mean right that's
what I mean also of course
so you keep changing you can get no but
if you change a lot but if you change
slightly then if it's invertible to
begin with a slight deformation slight
paration will remain invertible that's
why I say small paration and if you have
a non-invertible case if the determinant
is zero then even a very very slight
paration there is always a slight
paration if you say oh I want to
paration less than
0.001 I can always do that and then make
the determinant non zero
also in that in that
sense this determinant zero set or the
non inverti form a very thin set and the
rest the
majority is formed by
invols is that
clear yeah this is a quite important
Point thank you very much for raising
the
question if you want this most of the
space if you learn to that kind of
language you can say that this is the
open dense subset or in terms of
probability it's also probability one it
happens with probability one whereas the
rest happens with probability zero okay
so this is the situation now we have
already
proved that this statement
Falls that star in other words PQ and QT
have the same I
values
in this gener
experation so for most of the matrices
it's true so almost all the time this
statement is true almost all the
time PQ and QP have the same argum
values because this argument
applies okay now some of the time but
you'd better be really unlucky I mean
this is almost never going to happen it
happens with probability is zero okay
but it might happen that you are on a
noninvertible beginning with q might be
non-invertible in that case what do we
do yeah to prove p and star in the
degenerate
case
situation really unlucky situation so
it's
this station
okay let's choose so let's suppose
that Q is somewhere here really
unfortunate
okay choose
q1 sorry invertible
ones let's de form the problem q1 Q2 and
so on all of the invertible what I mean
is I can approximate this unfortunate
unlucky and degenerate
Q by a
sequence of matrices that converges to
this q but all of which approximations
are
invertible okay q1 Q2 and so
forth here is an
example this Matrix is of course not
invertible but I can approximate this by
invertible matrices for example 1 / n
for each n it's invertible and when I
take 1 / two 1 3 1/ 4 it's an
approximation and in the limit you
convert this Matrix okay so that's what
you
do that
converges in
that
converge to
two but let's now
revise am I doing the right thing yeah
I'm going to leave this
[Applause]
for ah okay I'm erasing the board in the
wrong way because I was expecting to
have two black bards there you see so
I'm a little confused I'm sorry about
this this I'm going to leave this and
then work on
that okay why don't I move there
so I'm going to get
better but look at that statement
star that PQ and QP have the same a
value well that
statement the
claim the
tends
continuously on
Q what I mean is if you have two
matrices A and B they have the same AR
value and if you change b a little
bit where A and B may no longer have the
same IG values but they have almost the
same IG values in that
I values of a matrix depend continuously
on The
Matrix that's clear because when you
change the Matrix where I vectors
directions might change slightly I
values might change slightly but okay
only
continuously
so we know
that star of end so to speak is
true for
pqn and q n p if you
like yeah in this approximation so for
each of these approximating matrices
here in this safe region we have the
statement and the statement is true here
it's true here it's true here it's true
here it's true here it's true here it's
true here it's true here it's true here
it's true here and when it converge it's
through
here because it's a continuous statement
as you take the
limit this is
true
also and that's really QED the end of
the
proof I hope that you enjoy this kind of
argument let's revise once again what we
did we wanted to prove that PQ and QP
had the same AG
values there was a very simple easy case
that we identified to begin with and
that's when Q was the invertible then
this identity straightforward shows you
that PQ and QP are similar conjugate
they matrices of the same linear
transformation so of course they have
the same AR
Valu but an objection was that maybe Q
is not invertible
it's then that topology starts kicking
in in fact topology started kicking in
already when we adopted the attitude of
looking at the simplest cases most
generic most common the majority of
cases we always begin by the generic
case and then worry about degeneracies
later in the degener case you realize
that you can approximate the degenerate
Case by the generic cases or if you like
we can deform de generate case two
generic cases and since for each of the
generic cases the statement is true and
because the statement is a continuous
statement I can take this approximation
and in the limit it's also true that's
the CR of
that
okay good
i' like to suggest then some
problems so those problems can be
done as
assignments how shall we call them and
because I don't want to call them
problems I might use the problem in some
other context let's call them projects
okay so project number one that you
might want to do is the investigation of
the movie
when you have n twists cut it along the
D line what happens project number
two
is prove
that for any every
say Square Matrix
L the determinant of the exponential of
this Matrix I shall make comment is
equal to exponential of the trace of
this
Matrix who among you has seen the
exponential of a matrix exponential
number everyone has seen exponential
Matrix have you
seen the simpl way to define it is as a
power series you take the exponential
power series and instead of the variable
you put the Matrix there and you can
show not to difficult that this series
converges in other words every element
of the Matrix entry of the Matrix
converges and that's the exponential
Matrix and it that's also a square
Matrix and if you take a determinant of
that it's the same as taking a trace of
the Matrix and taking the
exponential
interesting try to prove this by this
kind of argument topological approach by
deformation well it's easy I like to
give you a hint when L is
diagonal and you notice that most
matrices are
diagonalizable you might have learned
for example the theory of Jordan canical
form Jordan normal forms that appears
when the Matrix is not diagonalizable
but this
Theory beloved of instru of linear
algebra though it may be is kind of a
perverse Theory because most matrices
are diagonalizable you have to be really
unlucky for your random Matrix B non
diagonalizable okay another
project similar idea is
prove what is called K Hamilton
theor another classic theorem in linear
algebra
and again you note that K Hamilton
theorem is basically trivial when the
Matrix you have is diagonal but most
matrices are
dioniz
okay so those are two projects or
project so this is one single project
okay so
that's is that clear so one project is
movus and that's another project but it
has two parts because they can be done
by the same
idea and if you can think
of other
situations that are a meable that can be
solved by the same method that's great
so part
Infinity think of other
statements in linear
algebra or Matrix
theory that can
be proved in this Cas in this sense
topologically by the formation
[Music]
method that's a research problem
okay I'd like to before we close this
section this example make a comment
about the fact that PQ and QP always
have the same I
values a
remark this is one of those remarks
where you don't have to worry about if
you don't understand what I'm talking
about it will pass quickly so don't
worry
you have all seen what the trace of a
matrix is presumably the usual way to
define what the trace is is to take a
square Matrix and add all the diagonal
terms this plus this plus and that's the
trace but the much better way to think
about the trace is to say that it's the
sum of all the IG values that's a better
way to think about it similarly
determinant I don't know how you learned
what the determinant was one the ways of
thinking about the determinant is that
it's the product of all the I values
that's another way to think about
determinant so Trace is the sum of the
all the I
values
yeah so since that's the case since
Trace is the sum of all the
values the
relation soal commutation relation
that's so important in quantum
me it says that PQ minus QP equals some
multiple of the identity it's in fact
usually the H bar the CL constant times
the identity but you don't have to worry
about the time constant so PQ minus QP
is proportional to the identity
Matrix that's really Central to Quantum
Mechanics is impossible
it can never
happen why take the trace on both
sides and we get trace of PQ minus trace
of QP but that's zero because they have
the same
Trace yeah because this I values are the
same zero equals something trace of the
identity Matrix is not
zero
something non zero yeah n for example
yeah so this relationship can never
happen and yet quantum mechanics uses
this all the
time what's going
on maybe quantum mechanics is wrong it
is not wrong what it's saying that is
that in order to do quantum mechanics
you need infinite matri
so in finite dimensional space this is
impossible you have to do infinite
dimensional spaces and for those of you
who have learned about function analysis
linear operators and so on I like point
out that in fact that relationship is
impossible even for for bounded
operators on Hilbert and so on ban
spaces and so on if the operator is
bounded that cannot happen there's a
separate proof in finite dimensional
linear operators that's completely
impossible because of what we have
discussed but even in infinite
dimensional spaces for bounded operators
it doesn't work so quantum mechanics
must cannot avoid using unbounded
operators so all the theorems that we
learn about spectral resolutions of
bounded operators in hisory spaces and
so on that goes out of the window we
cannot use it in quantum mechanics
amazing
situation
okay good I would like to take a break
then we have been together for 1 hour
approximately for five minutes and then
we'll continue um I might talk a little
bit and then we'll start working on
yesterday's problems and then continue
okay